<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.5.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-01-20T17:16:46-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Shane Elipot</title><subtitle>Research Assist. Professor of Ocean Sciences at the University of Miami. Navigate above to know more.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">On the inappropriate use of variance-preserving spectra</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/variance-preserving-spectra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the inappropriate use of variance-preserving spectra" /><published>2020-01-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/variance-preserving-spectra</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/variance-preserving-spectra/">&lt;p&gt;Again and again I am dismayed by the habit of using &lt;em&gt;variance-preserving spectra&lt;/em&gt; to diagnose periodicities in time series. This habit is crawling steadily in the observational oceanographic literature (not so much in climate science, they know better). The reasons I can see for this serious problem are twofold: 1) the repeat of analyses from published papers which unfortunately passed the review process, and 2) the lack of statistical training of physical oceanographers. This last reason is unfortunate and should be corrected. Statistics is the science of collecting and analyzing numerical data so we should get on board.  Now, I am not claiming to be a statistician, but I humbly think that I spend more time than others thinking about statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I often talk with a couple of statisticians that deal with time series, I have casually asked them: “Why do you think people use variance-preserving spectra?”. Their answer was revealing: they did not even know what a variance-preserving spectrum was! Once I explained to them (see below), they were even more confused. They also wondered what was wrong with us (oceanographers). Besides that, what personally makes me sad is that we collectively spend millions of tax-payer dollars to obtain invaluable time series of oceanographic variables (such as oceanic volume transport), only to analyze them with the wrong tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than ranting without purpose, I have decided to write a little note to demonstrate why variance-preserving spectra should not be used to infer &lt;strong&gt;anything&lt;/strong&gt; about periodicity in a time series, and to suggest alternative methods. I have just become an assistant professor, yet one with the epithet &lt;em&gt;research&lt;/em&gt; in front, which means I do not teach (nor do I get paid for teaching). Don’t get me wrong, I am thrilled by this new position, but wish I could also teach. So here you go, I am putting out there a little lecture for whoever is interested. Let me know if I am doing it all wrong at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:selipot@rsmas.miami.edu&quot;&gt;selipot@rsmas.miami.edu&lt;/a&gt; or comment below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One definition of the frequency spectrum &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S(f)&lt;/script&gt; (there are several) is that it is the Fourier transform of the autocovariance function &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R(\tau)&lt;/script&gt;, or in other words, that the spectrum and the autocovariance function are &lt;em&gt;Fourier transform pairs&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;S(f) \equiv   \int_{-\infty}^{+\infty} e^{-i 2 \pi f \tau}  R(\tau) d\tau , \quad\quad R (\tau) = \int_{-\infty}^\infty e^{i 2 \pi f \tau}  S(f) \, df .&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Wiener-KhinchinTheorem.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wiener–Khintchine theorem&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. When the expression above is evaluated at zero lag &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(\tau=0)&lt;/script&gt;, one obtains that the variance of your time series, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma^2&lt;/script&gt;, is the integral of the frequency spectrum:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\sigma^2 \equiv R (0) = \int_{-\infty}^{+\infty} S(f) \, df .&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I think estimating a spectrum is the most useful: it shows the frequency decomposition of the variance of your time series. It allows you to state something about where the energy of your signal resides. If you are new to spectral analysis you could start with &lt;a href=&quot;https://selipot.github.io/talks/lecture4/index.html&quot;&gt;my lecture on time series analysis&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://jmlilly.net/course.html&quot;&gt;the entire course on the subject by my colleague oceanographer Jonathan Lilly&lt;/a&gt;. At the bottom of this post you will find also some good book references including the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511622762&quot;&gt;Percival and Walden (1993)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Spectral Analysis for Physical Applications&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to the topic of this post: another typical use of spectral (or harmonic) analysis in physical oceanography is to look for quasi-periodic signals in a time series, such as a &lt;em&gt;seasonal&lt;/em&gt; or an &lt;em&gt;annual&lt;/em&gt; cycle. People are looking for “peaks”, which amounts to looking for patterns in a time series. This seems to be a very human trait because in oceanography exactly periodic signals are actually rare, and purely monochromatic signals (one frequency) even more so. As a side note, a typical and erroneous interpretation of a spectrum I often hear is about a semi-annual peak (6-month period). Typically the reason for such a peak is not that there is a physical process at that specific frequency, but more likely that it is a harmonic of the annual, and lower, frequency. In other words you have a periodic signal with a 1-year period but it is not a pure sinusoid, and more than one frequency is needed to describe the periodic process (&lt;a href=&quot;http://mathworld.wolfram.com/FourierSeries.html&quot;&gt;Fourier series&lt;/a&gt; anyone?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I want to show a synthetic example of a time series that is not unlike many published oceanographic time series, and show how a variance-preserving spectral estimate of this time series can lead to misidentifying &lt;em&gt;peaks&lt;/em&gt;. Below is shown a randomly generated real-valued time series with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/script&gt; points. I generated and scaled this time series so that its variance is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;0.01&lt;/script&gt; and thus its standard deviation is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;0.1&lt;/script&gt;. With a trained eye you could almost see that staring at the plot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/timeseries.pdf&quot; alt=&quot;Matern process with N=1000&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time series is actually one realization of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nonlin-processes-geophys.net/24/481/2017/&quot;&gt;Matérn process&lt;/a&gt; with a spectrum given by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--- S(\omega) = \frac{\sigma^2 }{ (\omega^2+\lambda^2)^\alpha} \times \lambda^{(2\alpha-1)/C} $$ --&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;S(f) = C \frac{A^2}{[(2\pi f)^2+\lambda^2]^\alpha}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C&lt;/script&gt; is just a normalizing constant. To generate this time series I used a freely accessible Matlab toolbox called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jonathanlilly/jLab&quot;&gt;jLab&lt;/a&gt; written by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jmlilly.net&quot;&gt;Jonathan Lilly&lt;/a&gt;. I like this model because it fits nicely a lot of oceanographic time series I have looked at, including Lagrangian time series and time series of oceanic transports. In fact, I have used that model to model and test statistics of transport time series of the AMOC in my &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1175/JCLI-D-16-0664.1&quot;&gt;Elipot et al. 2017 paper&lt;/a&gt;. The point of using this model is that there is absolutely no periodicity in this signal; it has a continuous spectrum with no peak. What does a peak in a spectrum mean anyway? That the spectral power at a single frequency is much greater than neighboring frequencies, or that it is much more than what you would expect under the hypothesis that your observed process (i.e. time series) is representative of some noise-like process, white or colored. There is nothing wrong with a noise-like process by the way, on the contrary it tells you a lot about your observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, how does a spectral estimate of this time series look like? The next figure shows a &lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/1456701&quot;&gt;multitaper spectral estimate&lt;/a&gt; which is really one of the best methods around to estimate a spectrum in a non parametric way (i.e. not knowing its shape, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://selipot.github.io/talks/lecture4/index.html#50&quot;&gt;my lecture&lt;/a&gt; as an example on how to implement it practically). The estimate is shown in blue, the non-symmetric 95% confidence intervals are shown in lighter blue, and the theoretical spectrum is shown in red.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/spectra_linlin.pdf&quot; alt=&quot;Multitaper spectral estimate on linear scales&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may say that the &lt;em&gt;estimate&lt;/em&gt; in blue is very different from the &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; spectrum in red. That is however the nature of spectral estimation using finite time series and there is no added noise in the time series, only the process described by the theoretical spectrum. From finite data, the true spectrum is not accessible, it can only be estimated, sometimes poorly. By the way, with this plot, &lt;a href=&quot;https://selipot.github.io/talks/lecture4/index.html#49&quot;&gt;if you have scaled your spectrum properly&lt;/a&gt;, you can probably estimate the variance of the signal since it is the area under the curve according to the Wiener–Khintchine theorem given above (Here I would say that the area under the spectral estimate is about the area of the drawn triangle so approximately &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{2} \times (0.08 \times 0.3) \approx 0.01&lt;/script&gt; which is the variance I specified above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, because the variance of a typical time series in oceanography spans a very wide range of magnitude over a wide range of temporal scales, it is typical to plot a spectrum on a so-called log-log plot, that is with the two axes shown on a logarithm base 10 scale:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/spectra_loglog.pdf&quot; alt=&quot;Multitaper spectral estimate on base 10 logarithmic scales&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure this type of spectrum looks very familiar to many: a plateau towards the zero frequency, a shoulder break at mid-frequencies, and a power-law behavior at higher frequencies that manifests itself as a linear slope in this log-log representation. One issue with such log-log plot is that it really emphasizes the lowest frequencies which are nothing special compared to all the other ones in a statistical sense. However, we care about the lowest frequencies because we are often interested in long time scale processes. We typically received funding to collect an oceanographic time series for as long as we could and really would like to know about the period as long at the length of our experiment (hence use the multitaper that can achieve that, not the Welch’s method or anything like that!). Cool, now, see any peaks? Maybe, but really, there are NONE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now, let’s do like many do and plot a &lt;em&gt;variance-preserving spectrum&lt;/em&gt; instead (sometimes also called an &lt;em&gt;area-preserving plot&lt;/em&gt;). Such plot has nothing to do with the estimation of the spectrum itself, it’s just a different kind of plot. A google search leads to a note written by my PhD advisor (who knows a lot about statistics) about what that animal is. I think it is also described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/book/9780123877826/data-analysis-methods-in-physical-oceanography&quot;&gt;Emery and Thompson&lt;/a&gt;, as well as in &lt;a href=&quot;http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:HUL.InstRepos:15217585&quot;&gt;Carl Wunsch’s primer on time series analysis&lt;/a&gt;. Now, using the fact that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d(\ln(f)) = df/f&lt;/script&gt;, one can rewrite&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\sigma^2 = \int^{+\infty}_{-\infty} S(f) df = \int^{+\infty}_{-\infty} S(f)\, f d(\ln(f))&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\ln&lt;/script&gt; is the natural logarithm (logarithm base &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e&lt;/script&gt;) not the common logarithm (base 10). The idea behind this transformation is that when one plots &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S(f) \times f&lt;/script&gt; on the “y axis” versus &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\ln(f)&lt;/script&gt; on the “x axis”, the area under the curve between two frequencies is proportional to the variance in the range of frequencies defined by these two frequencies. It compensates for the “squeezing” of the high frequencies and the “stretching” of the low frequencies in the previous plot above. So now a variance preserving version of the previous plots is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/variancespectra.pdf&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;quot;Variance-preserving spectral estimate&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this plot the y-axis is in units of variance of your variable, and the x-axis is this weird logarithm unit (I am suspecting that the papers I have seen using this type of plots did not even pay attention to the distinction between logarithm base &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;10&lt;/script&gt; and logarithm base &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e&lt;/script&gt; in their calculations and potentially have a factor &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\log 10&lt;/script&gt; error for their variance estimates).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now, see any peaks? Well, if you did not know better, you would say that yeah perhaps there are peaks between &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-2&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-3&lt;/script&gt;. Hey, even the theoretical spectrum suggests that there is a “hill” near that range … wouldn’t that be a peak? No, but nevertheless, the frequencies near that hill are the frequencies for which the process represented by the Matérn spectrum transitions from a “white” (flat) type of spectrum to a power-law (self-similar) type of spectrum. This range of “transition” frequencies is actually controlled by the &lt;em&gt;damping&lt;/em&gt; parameter &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; of the theoretical spectrum. Go read &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5194/npg-24-481-2017&quot;&gt;Lilly et al. 2017&lt;/a&gt; to know more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the end, there are no peaks! Unfortunately, I have seen too many papers arbitrarily claiming that peaks existed based on a plot just like the one above. I bet that in most cases such erroneous diagnostics are the result of the misleading characteristics of the variance-preserving spectrum representation. I have actually not read any paper that use this representation for its alleged use of using the area under the curve to relatively quantify the distribution of variance. If you have, let me know, I’d be glad to be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in the end, how does one look for peaks? Well, this is actually not simple and this should be the subject of another post. One could start however by using the confidence intervals! Given the confidence intervals displayed in the linear or logarithmic plots above, one would be hard-pressed to state that there are any peaks in this example. Otherwise, I personally use a statistical test for periodicity in colored noise given by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/1456701&quot;&gt;Thomson (1982)&lt;/a&gt; and described nicely in &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511622762&quot;&gt;Percival and Walden, (1993)&lt;/a&gt;. Peaks in colored noise is the most common situation I have encountered in physical oceanography. I have coded it in Matlab, send me an &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:selipot@rsmas.miami.edu&quot;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt; and I’d be happy to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Matlab script to generate the figures above is available at a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/selipot/laughing-doodle&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511622762&quot;&gt;Percival, D. B. and Walden, A. T. (1993), &lt;em&gt;Spectral Analysis for ddPhysical Applications&lt;/em&gt;, Cambridge University Press&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wiley.com/en-us/Random+Data%3A+Analysis+and+Measurement+Procedures%2C+4th+Edition-p-9781118210826&quot;&gt;Bendat, J. S., &amp;amp; Piersol, A. G. (2011), &lt;em&gt;Random data: analysis and measurement procedures&lt;/em&gt; (Vol. 729), John Wiley &amp;amp; Sons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] Jenkins, G.M. and Watts, D. G. (1968), &lt;em&gt;Spectral Analysis and its Applications&lt;/em&gt;, Holden-Days.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Again and again I am dismayed by the habit of using variance-preserving spectra to diagnose periodicities in time series. This habit is crawling steadily in the observational oceanographic literature (not so much in climate science, they know better). The reasons I can see for this serious problem are twofold: 1) the repeat of analyses from published papers which unfortunately passed the review process, and 2) the lack of statistical training of physical oceanographers. This last reason is unfortunate and should be corrected. Statistics is the science of collecting and analyzing numerical data so we should get on board. Now, I am not claiming to be a statistician, but I humbly think that I spend more time than others thinking about statistics.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lectures on Methods of Data Analysis</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/statistics-lectures/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lectures on Methods of Data Analysis" /><published>2017-09-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/statistics-lectures</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/statistics-lectures/">&lt;p&gt;I just spent 3 very intense but delightful weeks in Cape Town, the mother city of South Africa. Aside from attending the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iapso-iamas-iaga2017.com&quot;&gt;IAPSO-IAMAS-IAGA 2017 meeting&lt;/a&gt; which was a lot of fun, I visited for two weeks the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sea.uct.ac.za&quot;&gt;Department of Oceanography at the University of Cape Town&lt;/a&gt; in order to deliver a series of lectures on methods of data analysis in oceanic and atmospheric sciences. I am very grateful to the Head of Department Prof. Isabelle Ansorge and Dr. Juliet Hermes from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.saeon.ac.za&quot;&gt;the South African Environmental Observation Network&lt;/a&gt; for making my visit possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My audience was broad and diverse (more than 30 students!), from Masters level to postdoctoral researchers. I am pleased to make now available openly on my website the &lt;a href=&quot;/talks/&quot;&gt;slides of these five lectures&lt;/a&gt;, as well as the Matlab scripts that the students worked with during afternoon practical sessions. I was ambivalent about making the students use a commercial software, as opposed to an open source software like Python. However, In the interest of time and exactness, I had to stick to what I knew. In addition, most of these Matlab scripts are compatible with the Matlab-like free software &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnu.org/software/octave/&quot;&gt;Octave&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I am always grateful to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jmlilly.net&quot;&gt;Jonathan Lilly&lt;/a&gt; who made me embark on this journey of lecturing on stats! And please check out the latest version of his course on time series analysis &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jmlilly.net/talks/oslo/v2/index.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to email me with comments or questions about this material!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lectures" /><summary type="html">I just spent 3 very intense but delightful weeks in Cape Town, the mother city of South Africa. Aside from attending the IAPSO-IAMAS-IAGA 2017 meeting which was a lot of fun, I visited for two weeks the Department of Oceanography at the University of Cape Town in order to deliver a series of lectures on methods of data analysis in oceanic and atmospheric sciences. I am very grateful to the Head of Department Prof. Isabelle Ansorge and Dr. Juliet Hermes from the South African Environmental Observation Network for making my visit possible.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hourly drifter product version 1.01 released</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/hourly-dataset-ver-1.01/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hourly drifter product version 1.01 released" /><published>2017-01-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/hourly-dataset-ver-1.01</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/hourly-dataset-ver-1.01/">&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce the release of version 1.01 of the hourly drifter product. Now available to download from the Global drifter program &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aoml.noaa.gov/phod/dac/hourly_data.php&quot;&gt;DAC website&lt;/a&gt;. The methods of interpolation implemented to generate this product are the same as for version 1.00 of the dataset released in mid-2016, see &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/2016JC011716&quot;&gt;Elipot et al. 2016, doi:10.1002/2016JC011716&lt;/a&gt;. See the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aoml.noaa.gov/phod/dac/hourly_data.php&quot;&gt;release notes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 1.01 update adds newer data to the previous version, one year of quality-controlled data up to 30 June 2016 for Argos-tracked drifters, and more than one year of GPS-tracked data, up to 1 October 2016. In addition, we have added data before 1 September 2005 (the start date of version 1.00) by considering all GPS-tracked drifters since the beginning of the GDP, and all Argos-tracked drifter data since the beginning of the GDP, when the average of the uneven sampling intervals per trajectory is less than or equal to 3 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/data_distribution_1.01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Alt text&quot; title=&quot;Distribution of hourly drifter position and velocity estimates from Argos-tracked and GPS-tracked trajectories, version 1.01&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1.01 dataset now totals over 117.4 million estimates of position and velocity with confidence intervals from 12,287 Argos-tracked drifter trajectories, and over 5.6 million estimates of position and velocity with confidence intervals from 985 GPS-tracked drifter trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simplified versions of the Matlab codes used to generate this dataset are available through a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/selipot/hourly-drifters/&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="drifters" /><summary type="html">We are pleased to announce the release of version 1.01 of the hourly drifter product. Now available to download from the Global drifter program DAC website. The methods of interpolation implemented to generate this product are the same as for version 1.00 of the dataset released in mid-2016, see Elipot et al. 2016, doi:10.1002/2016JC011716. See the release notes.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Colors of the Wind Ocean</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/colors-of-the-ocean/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colors of the &lt;strike&gt;Wind&lt;/strike&gt; Ocean" /><published>2016-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/colors-of-the-ocean</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/colors-of-the-ocean/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can own the earth and still&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All you’ll own is earth until&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can paint with all the Colors of the &lt;strike&gt;Wind&lt;/strike&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ocean&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rejectedbanana&quot;&gt;Kim Martini&lt;/a&gt; for pointing out on twitter a new article published in &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.5670/oceanog.2016.66&quot;&gt;Oceanography magazine&lt;/a&gt;! In that article, Thyng et al. present a set of freely available colormaps called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/matplotlib/cmocean&quot;&gt;cmocean&lt;/a&gt; to be used for oceanographic applications. This newish set strives to provide a selection of color palettes chosen to accurately serve the representation of data, with color hues we oceanographers traditionally associate with oceanic variables (such as deep blue to white for sea ice). The set is built in order for our eyes to not misinterpret the data being presented (the analog filter of our eyes perceive colors and color gradients unevenly). In particular, the method used by Thyng et al. consists in making sure the perceptual (visual) changes in a given colormap match the changes in the underlying data, using a property of color called “lightness”, and relies mostly on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/matplotlib/viscm&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;viscm&lt;/strong&gt; tool&lt;/a&gt;. Appropriately, The authors point out the pitfalls of the &lt;em&gt;jet&lt;/em&gt; colormap (which I have always personally found evil), and I think they are right on point when assigning the apparent popularity of that colormap to having been the default &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathworks.com/help/matlab/ref/colormap.html&quot;&gt;MATLAB colormap&lt;/a&gt; for many years (but recently switched to the demure parula colormap by the way).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business of colors can be incredibly complicated, but also very useful. I am very keen on using the &lt;em&gt;phase&lt;/em&gt; information of data, which is a challenging thing to represent when an associated magnitude is also present. In several of my papers I have relied on the Hue-Saturation-Value (HSV) properties of colors rather than the more traditional Red-Green-Blue (RGB) representation (see as an example my 2016 paper &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1175/JPO-D-14-0254.1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Characteristics, Energetics, and Origins of Agulhas Current Meanders and their Limited Influence on Ring Shedding&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). Another example on the use of colors in oceanography is the paper by Hughes and Williams in 2010 called &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2010JC006102&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The color of sea level&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; who smartly used colors to represent 3D information of sea level spectra on the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, check out this new paper and the refrences therein if you are interested in colors!: &lt;em&gt;True Colors of Oceanography Guidelines for Effective and Accurate Colormap Selection&lt;/em&gt; (2016) By Kristen M. Thyng, Chad A. Greene, Robert D. Hetland, Heather M. Zimmerle, and Steven F. DiMarco, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.5670/oceanog.2016.66&quot;&gt;doi:10.5670/oceanog.2016.66&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Pocahontas&lt;/em&gt; is my second favorite Disney movie, yes, after &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;) …&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="colormap," /><category term="oceanography," /><category term="matlab" /><summary type="html">You can own the earth and still</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Things reviewers say</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/things-reviews-say/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Things reviewers say" /><published>2016-09-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/things-reviews-say</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/things-reviews-say/">&lt;p&gt;I found somehow reassuring to read in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://eos.org/editors-vox/stuff-my-reviewers-say?utm_source=eos&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=EosBuzz092316&quot;&gt;blog post of  EOS&lt;/a&gt; that the Editor in Chief of Geophysical Research Letters, no less, recently had a manuscript rejected for publication. He wrote that &lt;em&gt;“this rejection was particularly deflating, both because I had invested two years in the science, and because two of the three reviewers dismissed the very conception of the analysis.”&lt;/em&gt; I see this as being told that your paper sucks because your analysis sucks in the first place. &lt;em&gt;Ouch&lt;/em&gt;. We’ve all had at least one terrible story about a particular set of reviews. It turns out that last week was &lt;a href=&quot;https://peerreviewweek.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Peer Review Week&lt;/a&gt;! Who knew?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I found funny is that following this rejection one of his students introduced him to &lt;a href=&quot;http://shitmyreviewerssay.tumblr.com&quot;&gt;“Shit my reviewers say”&lt;/a&gt;, the excellent tumblr account which is also on twitter as &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/YourPaperSucks&quot;&gt;@YourPaperSucks&lt;/a&gt; and has been a favorite of mine for some time. If you did not know this wonderful resource of procrastination, happy reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review," /><category term="publications" /><summary type="html">I found somehow reassuring to read in a blog post of EOS that the Editor in Chief of Geophysical Research Letters, no less, recently had a manuscript rejected for publication. He wrote that “this rejection was particularly deflating, both because I had invested two years in the science, and because two of the three reviewers dismissed the very conception of the analysis.” I see this as being told that your paper sucks because your analysis sucks in the first place. Ouch. We’ve all had at least one terrible story about a particular set of reviews. It turns out that last week was Peer Review Week! Who knew?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">On the new standard of sharing your code</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/the-new-standard-of-sharing-code/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the new standard of sharing your code" /><published>2016-09-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/the-new-standard-of-sharing-code</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/the-new-standard-of-sharing-code/">&lt;p&gt;Scientists in general, and oceanographers in particular, have been used for many years to sharing “their” data. A few whine about how difficult it is to obtain funding and acquire the data, and as such should keep their exclusivity. They can for a few years, but in the end it is not really their data anyway, since they most likely originate from projects funded by tax payers, through governmental funding agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something new is happening though. Recently, as part of the last checks before one of our newest manuscript got accepted, we were asked by the journal editor to disclose the “availability of our code”. Obviously, stating that our messy, uncommented, code written for the commercial software MATLAB was not available, was not acceptable. I was first annoyed at the daunting task of putting together a sharable code but mostly I was surprised. I was surprised because our methods involved relatively standard statistical techniques and tools, and a few relatively unusual ones that were otherwise clearly referenced in our “methods” section. What I mean is that the references given in our article clearly spelled out the formulae used. As an example, I have become really fond of &lt;em&gt;kernel estimators&lt;/em&gt; and the Nadaraya-Watson estimator with a Gaussian or an Epachnikov kernel has become my go-to for non-parametric curve estimation. The book &lt;em&gt;Local Polynomial Modelling and Its Applications&lt;/em&gt; by Fan and Gijbels is a very nice introduction to these methods. So, in the end, not only do we have to say with words, or equations, what we did, but we also have to type it up for others. Isn’t that too much?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am being sarcastic and it looks like this is the way forward anyway, so the old guard better adapt, and students better get acquainted right away with these methods. The goal is to improve reproducibility of results (especially in wet labs), and as such some journals have started to hire editors for that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/news/why-scientists-must-share-their-research-code-1.20504&quot;&gt;purpose&lt;/a&gt;. Thank you to my colleague &lt;a href=&quot;http://ryan.actualscience.net&quot;&gt;Ryan Abernathey&lt;/a&gt; for tweeting this article. In addition, it apperas that
one of the  points of this movement is to improve the quality of scientific code. That means clear structure, organization, testing, comments, and documentation.
Scripps graduate student Cesar rocha’s recent project is apparently a very good &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/crocha700/UpperOceanSeasonality&quot;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;. Another example is veteran oceanographer &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.uvic.ca/~jklymak&quot;&gt;Jody Klymak&lt;/a&gt; is making available a lot of his analysis code through his &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jklymak?tab=repositories&quot;&gt;GitHub page&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, my collaborator &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jmlilly.net&quot;&gt;Jonathan Lilly&lt;/a&gt; at NorthWest Research Associates has been working very hard for many years to put together his superb Matlab Toolbox called Jlab. It is distributed through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/52885-jlab--a-matlab-toolbox-for-data-analysis?requestedDomain=www.mathworks.com&quot;&gt;Matworks File Exchange&lt;/a&gt; but it is also on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jonathanlilly/jLab&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; for suggesting edits and modifications. GitHub watch out, here I come. (This site is hosted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="code," /><category term="data," /><category term="sharing," /><category term="GitHub" /><summary type="html">Scientists in general, and oceanographers in particular, have been used for many years to sharing “their” data. A few whine about how difficult it is to obtain funding and acquire the data, and as such should keep their exclusivity. They can for a few years, but in the end it is not really their data anyway, since they most likely originate from projects funded by tax payers, through governmental funding agencies.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Launch of new personal site on GitHub</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/shane-elipot-site-launched/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Launch of new personal site on GitHub" /><published>2016-09-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/shane-elipot-site-launched</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/shane-elipot-site-launched/">&lt;p&gt;I finally got around to put my new professional website together! It is powered by &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; and currently hosted, for free, on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. I browsed many resources to approximately understand how this works, and learned to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://git-scm.com&quot;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; at a basic level with the online tutorial &lt;a href=&quot;https://try.github.io/levels/1/challenges/1&quot;&gt;tryGit&lt;/a&gt;. I followed the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jmcglone.com/guides/github-pages/&quot;&gt;simple tutorial&lt;/a&gt; by Jonathan Mcglone, but then opted for the free Jekyll theme &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mmistakes/so-simple-theme&quot;&gt;So Simple&lt;/a&gt;.  In the process, I downloaded a free text editor called &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; which I find very neat, at least on Mac OS X. You can easily download a package for Atom that will allow you to use Emacs keybindings, which I am used to.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll," /><category term="git," /><category term="Atom," /><category term="GitHub" /><summary type="html">I finally got around to put my new professional website together! It is powered by Jekyll and currently hosted, for free, on GitHub. I browsed many resources to approximately understand how this works, and learned to use git at a basic level with the online tutorial tryGit. I followed the simple tutorial by Jonathan Mcglone, but then opted for the free Jekyll theme So Simple. In the process, I downloaded a free text editor called Atom which I find very neat, at least on Mac OS X. You can easily download a package for Atom that will allow you to use Emacs keybindings, which I am used to.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry></feed>